this video is sponsored by app
cloud test their servers with
storage faster than any
ssd for free and get $25
credit with the promo code
beta tec hello and welcome one
more day to beta tech for those of you who are
new to the channel here we talk about
software and technology and specifically
in this series we talk about
design patterns we are going to explain one by one each
design pattern looking at their uses and
explaining them with examples if you still don't
know what a design pattern is I'll
leave the index of the series
up here and in the description and today we are going to
talk about one of the most
famous patterns a pattern that is surely one of the
most searched for on google and that
also has quite a bit of controversy we are
talking about the singleton pattern and
regarding the controversy I want to make
a small note before going
directly into the subject in this video I am going to
talk about the singleton on a technical level what it
is and what it is for so I am not going to
get into the discussion about whether it is a
pattern if it is an anti-pattern if it is right
or wrong to use it or anything like that I'll
leave you at the end of the video and in  the
description some small comments
it's about a little bit because some people
think it's good and other people think it
's wrong so without much further ado let's
see what singleton is trying to achieve and
how it does it
[Music]
the objective of using the
singleton pattern is to ensure that there is
only one instance of a
specific class in fact what is
achieved by implementing this pattern is
that it is impossible to instantiate more than one
instance of this class more than one object that is to
say it is not a pattern that is used
when for some reason you want to have
only one instance of a specific class
but when you want to absolutely not be able to
have more than one part of
making sure that we are always
using the same instance
singleton provides
global accessibility to this instance so that we
can get access to it from any
part of our program there are many
cases where you may simply want to
have an object of a class and really
nothing will happen nothing prevents you from having in
your project a class that only has one
instance in most cases you do not
need it to explicitly be a
singleton in fact there are very few
use cases where it is actually recommended to
use this pattern so despite
being a fairly simple pattern to
implement I think it is used in
texts  wrong a possible
use case for this pattern and perhaps the only one is
to manage resources that
can only be accessed individually
resources which you need to control
from the entire application the
common example that is always explained is that of a
log file where you need you can
manage this access to the file
in a centralized way and surely you do not
want to have multiple instances
writing to the same file
although let's be honest in other
videos we have seen how depending on the
architecture of your application it can be
perfectly normal to have multiple
instances of a log manager because
in the end it depends a lot on the use and your
intuition of whether you think that in the future you will only
need one instance the fact
of using a singleton or not but then
if what you do singleton is to avoid being
able to create more than one instance as it
does as programming you get
that behavior in the end if I have
a class and I call the constructor of that
class several times I am making several
instances this is not how you program a
singleton to avoid that this can
happen now we will explain how
a single toner would be implemented in
detail
but before explaining
the code specifically let me thank the
sponsor of this video  app cloud
offers both an app and a
super intuitive yet very
powerful control panel that allows you to automate the
scalability of your products in addition
all its servers have the
maximum ps technology that offers
faster disk speeds than
any ssd you can try flash for
free using the beta
text code and I'll leave it in the description and you will
also receive 25 dollars of credit
to use on the platform
implementing the singleton pattern is
achieved by playing with a very
funny little trick that can make you feel a
bit like a hacker sometimes it's about
making the constructor private by
making the constructor private
we make it inaccessible from
outside so that it is inaccessible from outside
the class therefore we gain control
over the instance of it or rather it
is the class itself that
gains control over how
its own objects are instantiated that is to say in
other words we block anyone
from outside the class itself from being able to
create instances of it
we prevent you from being able to write the normal
neither a class name nor a singleton you
cannot go around instantiating as
if nothing was happening the way in which
instance  you will make that specific class is
with another function normally this other
function is used there market
instance or something similar something that
indicates that you are obtaining the
instance of the singleton and this function will be in
charge internally of
constructing this instance this function
being part of the class can call the
private constructor without problem and
therefore can do one thing check
if any other instance
created previously already exists it checks if
an instance of this class already exists and if so
the function always returns it if it does
not exist before returning it it creates
a new one it creates it for the first time with
this that we achieve we achieve that there is
always only one instance
created of this class since if we try
to instantiate it again as the
only method with which we can do it
the distance with tests if they already existed
and we are always obtaining the first one
that we have created also with the fact of
having made this function static ty
instance we gain global access to this
function since it is not part of any
specific instance it is part of the
class itself therefore from any side
of our project we can obtain the
instance of this class that obviously
also has to be static it is the
responsibility of the singleton class to
save this instance to maintain
this static instance so that the
get instance function can access
it check if it exists or not and with
this we would have a singleton set up
the truth is that it is relatively
easy to write every time we
want to get the instance within
the getty instance function what we do
is check if it is already an instance of a1
and we are going to return it in this way
we always have the same we only have
a single copy a single object a
single instance of this class in the end
in summary what a singleton does is
encapsulate the instance creation process I do
n't know how many times I have said
already instance in this video
and encapsulate the object creation process
to a global function and removing it does
not take away like the power to be able to
make instances it takes away the constructor
of the class to prevent you from being able to create
more objects in a class that tells you hey
I have already created one I am going to give you the
same I am not going to create more for you it prevents you from being
able to instantiate more than one class the
practice is how to delegate the ownership of
a global variable to a class and
check if the object already exists over and over
again as I said at the beginning
singleton is a structure that creates
quite controversial in the end we always
try to avoid global variables
and it seems that this pattern is nothing more
than a global variable within a
class there is a super interesting talk
but a bit long it is about 50
minutes titled global state and
singletons given by me choose to see and in
2008 I leave the link here and in the
description in this talk
some possible dangers of using a
singleton are discussed and why sometimes it is thought that it is
wrong to use them between them and what I
agree with the most is the argument
that using this pattern complicates
my testing unnecessarily
normally when you make
unitary text you want to be able to have control
over the instances that you are generating
in order to
configure the tests to the extent that you
want it to do this that is the
other that this gives me this object
blah blah blah we have said it with a singleton it is
always returned in the same
instance so you have to do
many inelegant things some
tricks to be able to obtain
special instances
manipulated instances to be able to control the text that is to
say as much as in your project
you want there to be only one instance of
something the chances are that in reality you
need  at least two the one
used in the natural execution of your
code and the one used in
unit tests and yes I know that there are ways to
democratize or replace classes at
runtime and do things like
this but they are still patches that
surely would not be necessary if you did
not use this structure ultimately I
leave this video here because I think it
is very interesting and you can
go much deeper into this topic there is
a set of talks that are
quite good I hope that this
explanation has been useful to us and I
encourage you to let me know
if you want singleton is an anti-
pattern I do not think we can have a
pleasant debate on this subject seeing
different opinions and possible
use cases that you may have found
throughout these projects I encourage you to
tell us what you think about it in
the comments and without much more
thank you very much for watching me and I will see you
in the next video goodbye